(upbeat music)
- Hello, English learners.
Welcome back to English Pod.
My name is Marco.
- And I'm Erica.
- We're bringing you an
advanced lesson today.
- That's right.
An advanced lesson where we talk
about investing in emerging markets.
- Right.
So it's kind of a business topic.
It's kind of a world topic as well.
- Yes.
- And it's pretty difficult.
- Yeah, it is really hard.
- Right.
So if you're listening
and you don't understand
everything, please
don't get discouraged.
Don't worry about it.
Because we're here to learn.
- Yes, and we're here to help you.
- Right.
- So let's get started with this.
I'm really excited about this lesson.
- Yeah, okay.
Well, Marco, maybe
you can tell us a little bit.
What is an emerging market?
- An emerging market is a
market that is starting to develop.
- Okay.
- And it's growing rapidly.
- So you can maybe give some
examples of emerging market.
- Well, for example, China
is an emerging market.
- Yeah.
- In the last years, it's
been growing rapidly.
- More and more people are moving to
the middle class and have money to spend.
- Right, exactly.
- So China is like a really great
example of an emerging market.
- All right, well with that, let's listen
to the dialogue for the first time.
(upbeat music)
- Dad, I'd like to borrow some money.
- Sure, Johnny, how much
do you know, five bucks?
- Come on, Dad, I need 30,000.
I want to get into the market.
You know, I'm tired
of hearing all this news
about the economic downturn,
the inevitable recession,
people stuffing their
money in their mattresses.
I look at this as an opportunity.
This is a chance for me to get a
jumpstart on building my nest egg.
- I don't know about that, huh?
With all the uncertainty
in the markets right
now, to be very unwise
decision to invest.
I don't know if you're
aware, son, but there has
been a lot of turmoil
in the markets recently.
And there have already been half a
million layoffs in the last few months.
And we have no idea how the proposed stimulus
package will impact upon the economy.
There's just too much instability.
I just wouldn't feel comfortable
investing in this climate.
- But look at it this way, every
challenge is an opportunity.
And anyway, I'm not talking about
investing in the domestic market.
There are emerging markets
that promise great returns.
Look at China, for example.
They have 1.4 billion people,
half a billion of whom have
recently entered the middle class.
Here alone, the aggregate
demand for consumer goods
represents an amazing
wealth generating opportunity.
- Ah, come on, son, you're
looking at this too naively.
The Chinese market has
exhibited a great deal of instability
and that currency has been devalued
by almost a whole percentage point.
- Fine, then.
If that's the way you feel, so be it.
But you're losing out on
a great opportunity here.
I'm gonna hit up mom for the cash.
(upbeat music)
- Well, it sounds like
the dad has missed out
on a really big investment
opportunity, hey?
- Yeah, and his son is pretty smart.
- Yeah, pretty smart little boy.
- Uh-huh.
- Okay, so we have some great
words that we wanna look at here.
Why don't we start with
the first one, turmoil?
- turmoil.
So we have some great examples of
how turmoil is used in different sentences.
So let's listen.
- Example one.
- With a civil war, a famine and inflation,
the country has been
in turmoil for 10 years.
- Example two.
- There's been a lot of
turmoil in my life recently.
Back with to a new city, I've changed
my job, and I broke up with my girlfriend.
- Example three.
The devaluation of the dollar caused
a great deal of turmoil in the markets.
- So turmoil is a state of uncertainty
of change, of difficult times.
- A little bit of chaos.
- Yeah, yeah, yeah.
So, for example, when there's
a lot of turmoil in the market,
that means stock prices are
changing drastically from day to day.
- Right, or the economies in turmoil.
There's a lot of problems going on.
- Yeah, uncertainty.
- Uncertainly, okay.
Good word.
- All right, and we also saw
something really interesting
in the dialogue about a
proposed stimulus package.
- A proposed stimulus package.
- So a proposed stimulus package
is something that's going on now.
- Yes, let's break this phrase down.
So we've got stimulus package.
- A stimulus package, something
to stimulate the economy, right?
- Right, so money from the
government to get the economy moving.
- To get it moving, a stimulus package.
- Proposed, it means that
it hasn't been approved yet.
- Right, it's suggested.
- It's suggested, it's an idea.
So the proposed stimulus package for the
US economy, for example, is $150 billion.
- Right, that's $150 billion
of American taxpayers' money
that the government wants
to put into the economy
to keep it moving, to
keep it moving, right?
So if it works or not, that's still a
debate, but it's a proposed stimulus package.
- Let's move to our third phrase.
- Aggregate demand.
- So demand is pretty clear,
but this word aggregate.
What's that about?
- Aggregate is like a
combined added, right?
- Yeah.
- Aggregate demand.
For example, in a country like China,
where cities like in
Shanghai or cities like Beijing,
where more and more
people are accumulating
wealth, the aggregate
demand is increasing.
- Right, right, the combined demand
for consumer goods is growing.
- Right, more people have more
money, so they're spending more.
- Yes, okay.
- You know Marco, there's a ton of excellent
language in this dialogue, isn't there?
- Yeah, a lot of good stuff here.
- Yeah, and we wanna listen to the
dialogue one more time, but before we do,
we have three words for you
that we want you to listen for.
- Yeah, pay attention to these words.
Nest egg.
- Nest egg.
- Inevitable.
- And hit up, hit up.
So from the context of the dialogue,
try and see if you can figure
out what they mean, but after
listening to it, we'll come
back and explain it anyways.
(upbeat music)
- Dad, I'd like to borrow some money.
- Sure, Johnny, how much
do you know, five bucks?
- Come on, Dad, I need 30,000.
I wanna get into the market, you know?
I'm tired of hearing all this news
about the economic downturn,
the inevitable recession,
people stuffing their
money in their mattresses.
I look at this as an opportunity.
This is a chance for me to get a
jumpstart on building my nest egg.
- I don't know about that, huh?
With all the uncertainty
in the markets right
now, to be very unwise
as you can do invest.
I don't know if you're aware, son,
but there has been a lot of
turmoil in the markets recently.
And there have already been half a
million layoffs in the last few months,
and we have no idea how the proposed stimulus
package will impact upon the economy.
There's just too much instability.
I just wouldn't feel comfortable
investing in this climate.
- I'm looking at this way.
Every challenge is an opportunity.
And anyway, I'm not talking about
investing in the domestic market.
There are emerging markets
that promise great returns.
Look at China, for example.
They have 1.4 billion people,
half a billion of whom have
recently entered the middle class.
Here alone, the aggregate
demand for consumer goods
represents an amazing
wealth generating opportunity.
- Oh, come on, son, you're
looking at this too naively.
The Chinese market
has exhibited a great deal
of instability, and
that currency has been
devalued by almost a
whole percentage point.
- Fine, then.
If that's the way you feel, so be it.
But you're losing out on
a great opportunity here.
I'm gonna hit up mom for the cash.
- So the kid wants to invest because
he wants to set up his nest egg.
- That's right.
So basically he wants
to get a bunch of cash
together so that he can
buy a house or get married
or whatever, it's that money
you need to start your life, right?
- To start your life, you're nest egg.
It's kind of a weird way of
referring to this money, right?
- I guess it is kind of funny.
And also the little boy talked
about an inevitable recession.
- Yes, inevitable.
- Inevitable.
- Inevitable basically means unavoidable.
- Right.
- So this guy thinks that
the recession is unavoidable.
- It's gonna happen.
- Yes, inevitable.
You know, this word inevitable.
If you apply the root
word, you can get a noun
and adjective or an ad verb, right?
- Right.
- So we've got some examples
where you can see this word in action.
- Example one.
- Jason knew he was going to get laid off,
but he was trying to delay the inevitable.
- Example two.
- As a new manager, it's inevitable
that you're going to make mistakes.
- Example three.
- Inevitably, we all die
at the end of our lives.
- So as you can see, the noun
and adjective form are the same.
- Yes, inevitable.
- When we use it as an ad
verb though, we add the LY to it.
- Inevitably.
- Yes.
- So yeah, as you can see, we can use it
in many different ways
depending on what we want to say.
- Right, well inevitably, we have
to move on to our third words.
- Hit up, hit up.
- So he says he's going
to hit up mom for the cash.
- Ask his mom.
- Yeah, hit up.
- Yeah, this is kind of
a slangy term, isn't it?
- Yeah, it's more
informal, a lot more slangy.
We wouldn't really use it
with your boss with you.
- No, you're not going
to go up to your boss and
say, hey, I need to hit
you up for some cash.
- No.
- So Marco, I think this word is
only applying to money, right?
- Well, you wouldn't go
up to your boss and say,
oh, I need to hit you up
for some vacation time.
- No, it's typically used
for money in this context.
- Yeah, hit him up.
- We've got some examples
of the phrase, hit up.
Let's listen.
- Example one.
- I'm going to hit at the boss for a race.
- Example two.
- Are you trying to hit me up for money?
- Example three.
- I don't have any cash.
If you try hitting up Sophie, she's rich.
- Okay, so this is our
first advanced lesson.
I hope you enjoyed it.
It is a lot more challenging, I think.
- Yes.
- Especially because it's
set in a business context,
so we have a lot of specific words
and a lot of the technical vocabulary.
- That's right.
Marco, you're exactly right.
And I think that our users
are going to have a lot
of questions about the
language in this lesson.
So I'd like to invite you guys to
come onto our website at EnglishPod.
com.
- Exactly.
You can leave all your questions and
comments and we'll be there to answer them.
But until then, it's.
- Goodbye.
(upbeat music)